<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Tze Min's commonplace journal</title><link>https://commonplace-journal.pages.dev</link><description>Here, I write about my everyday learnings, including my notes, thoughts and references.</description><lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2024 08:15:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Getting into urban sketching</title><link>https://commonplace-journal.pages.dev/pages/getting-into-urban-sketching.html</link><guid>646b9aa7cc1d490ff0bd76e246277b8b</guid><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;body data-tags="art"&gt;
&lt;header&gt;
&lt;title&gt;Getting into urban sketching&lt;/title&gt;
&lt;/header&gt;
&lt;nav class="page-nav"&gt;Return to &lt;a href="../index.html"&gt;home&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;div class="main-bar"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Getting into urban sketching&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Materials used&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted the cheap stuff to play around with first, though my collection of cheap materials grew rapidly over the span of a year, until they were... no longer that cheap when accounted for in total:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Pencils&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pentel Energize 0.5: 1.80SGD, from Popular&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Faber-Castell 12 Classic Colour Pencils: 6SGD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Ink&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sakura Pigma Micron 01, 03 and 05: 2.40SGD each, from Popular&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Brushes&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Daler-Rowney All Purpose Synthetic Brush Set: 15 SGD, from Art Friend&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flat Wash, size 1/2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Round, sizes 10, 4 and 5/10&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Paints&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Watercolour&lt;/b&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Faber-Castell 12 watercolours (including a small brush): 8 SGD, from Popular&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Derwent Academy Watercolour Paints (24 tubes): 9.90SGD, after a sale's discount, from Popular&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Gouache&lt;/b&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Daler-Rowney Simply Opaque Watercolor Gouache (12x): 14SGD, from Art Friend&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Palettes&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plastic palette that holds 20 colours: 3SGD, from Popular&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Paper&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ecomaz travel journal: 15SGD, from Grassroots Book Room&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Monjojo Watercolor pad (A4 size/20 sheets/220 gsm/cold-pressed): 7.90SGD, from Popular&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Monjojo Watercolor pad (A5 size/20 sheets/220 gsm/cold-pressed): 4SGD, from Popular&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Masking tape&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scotch blue original multi-surface painter's tape (24mm), from Art Friend&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Painter's Mate Green tape (6mm x 55m), from Art Friend&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How I got into it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I listed a whole lot of materials up there, but I don't think... I need them all. They were bought either when discounted or when I wanted to try out a medium for the first time. Currently, the stuff I wanted to try evolved this way:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Travel journalling, because I had several overseas trips coming up and I'd bought my ecomaz travel notebook on a whim. This initially involved way more writing than drawing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pencil sketches of the places I went to and the food I ate. It was easier to draw food, even an impression of it, than describe it with words.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Found an old black ink pen (a freebie from a college career fair years ago) and my drawings became ink sketches.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Got my hands on a set of cheap Faber-Castell colour pencils, and soon those sketches filled with color.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My colouring always looked flat. Some searching of tutorials later, I figured out how to shade and blend with colour pencils, and soon I came across the idea of urban sketching online. Most urban sketchers used fineliner pens and watercolours.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My black ink pen was too thick and kept smudging. Went out and bought myself a fineliner, a Sakura Micron 0.3. With it, I started to draw buildings. They didn't look great because I made mistakes everywhere, but I discovered I could greatly improve them (aka cover up mistakes) by colouring them in. I did so with the coloured pencils.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A friend invites me out to use their watercolours. I try that for the first time and discover my ecomaz journal could, in fact, hold water-based paints.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I buy the cheapest watercolour paint set. By Faber-Castell, it came with 12 cakes, a built-in palette and a little brush. All I needed was an extra plastic container to hold water, of which I had many at home. My buildings and random urban scenery became outlined with ink first, then filled with watercolor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could've stopped there. But the more I tried watercolouring and the more artists I followed, the more I began to realise several limitations with the materials I had. Water dried rapidly on the ecomaz journal's paper and the round brush that came with the Faber-Castell paint set didn't hold much water, so I'd run out of paint quickly in my strokes. It resulted in having to put more layers of paint on the paper, but this made the latter look roughed-up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was also encountering other issues like being unable to try out most of the watercoloring techniques I read about online (mostly because of the paper's absorbency), and the paper wrinkling from the water. My small round brush didn't let me paint large surfaces easily. Plus, I began to want more colours, because who doesn't want more colours?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the minute I saw an 80% discount on 24 tubes of watercolor paint, I got them, alongside a cheap plastic palette and watercolour paper. I went out of my way to get gouache, this opaque watercolour I've heard so much about, because I figured I might as well try it. I was also given a set of Daler-Rowney brushes, some painter's tape and additional watercolor paper as a gift, though to be honest painter's tape was overkill... masking tape would've been fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Impact of materials on watercolour/gouache painting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of these are obvious in hindsight, but I only really understood it when I tried it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good brush that holds large amounts of water really makes a difference in how often you need to pick up paint from the palette. The Daler-Rowney round brush was about the same size as the Faber-Castell round brush, but the former gives me such awesome control over where I want the paint to go on the paper as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watercolor paper (or anything with a high percentage of cotton in them) allows water to sit on the surface for a longer time, which means you start being able to do the typical techniques you hear about online, e.g. wet on wet, dragging, charging. But painting on such paper felt like learning a whole new practice again, because I'd gotten used to painting on the ecomaz paper, in terms of how much water I should mix into the paint, how long I should wait for a layer to dry before putting on the second one, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven't noticed a huge difference, paint-wise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Impact of materials on sketching&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used to never understand the appeal of using ink. What if you messed up? But I really get it now. It's to make you commit to your strokes, because they're not erasable like pencils are. If you make a mistake, you just work with it, and if it really can't be salvaged, you could always start over. It's not the end of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I never went back to my old ink pen (that was thick and easily smudged) after getting the fineliner, because the latter gave me a lot more control over my strokes, which also became more even.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I noticed, however, was just how many lines my sketches seemed to have by the end of a session. Too many lines, sometimes, that it can be difficult to pick out details until I colour them in. But I was watching TobySketchLoose talk about keeping two different sizes of fineliners on hand, one thin and one thick, in his &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/DdbQLBdhMcY?feature=shared"&gt;Urban Sketching for Beginners - Step by Step - Tutorial&lt;/a&gt;. It made sense, varying the lines' sizes to make your drawings interesting, less uniform. I wanted at least several of my sketches to be able to stand alone, rather than get propped up by colors all the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tutorials referenced&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't want to pressure myself; journaling gave my mind clarity. But that doesn't mean I don't want to improve my sketching skills, because drawing and painting engaged me with my surroundings, made me pay attention to them, and as a result, made me remember what I'd been doing and where I'd been.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These YouTubers' videos helped me make better - and more fun - sketches:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TobySketchLoose: &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/DdbQLBdhMcY?feature=shared"&gt;Urban Sketching for Beginners - Step by Step - Tutorial&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finelinernerd: &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/aOSaQ50xeAM?feature=shared"&gt;5 Easy &amp;amp; Essential Watercolor Techniques for Beginners&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10,000hrs: &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/Q2_zpl738Kw?feature=shared"&gt;The Books I Use to Self-Learn Art --- general to specific&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;JakeDontDraw: &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/kz5b68rNkyw?feature=shared"&gt;Theres NO NEED to draw the features! Dont Get stuck drawing #arttip #art&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also relied on books, which I completed to varying degrees:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sketch Now, Think Later, by Mike Daikubara&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drawing on the Right Side of the Brain, by Betty Edwards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to Draw: Drawing and Sketching Objects and Environments From Your Imagination, by Scott Robertson, Thomas Bertling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Techniques&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mike Daikubara's Sketch Now, Think Later was the first "art" book I read. Much of how I approach urban sketching, and how I define urban sketching, came from it, little nuggets of advice that are more practical than really technique:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's okay to stand while sketching. It keeps you alert of your surroundings, which is always important, especially in an urban setting. But it also encourages you to move around and find the angle of the subject you want to draw.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't be afraid to draw over your original sketch with ink if you make a mistake. E.g. if you're drawing a car tyre and it's too big the first time, just draw over it the second or third time, confidently, and correct the shape. Very quickly, the mistake blends into the drawing itself and gives it character.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When watercolouring or filling in details with ink, there's no need to colour or shade every inch or every detail. You could do it for a small area, e.g. outline a few bricks here and there in a building and colour them in. Making mere suggestions of the texture and colours is enough for a sketch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Always finish your sketches.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;]]&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate></item><item><title>Explaining git to the layperson</title><link>https://commonplace-journal.pages.dev/pages/explaining-git-to-the-layperson.html</link><guid>f5073e8cc50425ed816ae6b675a394c8</guid><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;body data-tags="tech and data; mentorship"&gt;
&lt;header&gt;
&lt;title&gt;Explaining git to the layperson&lt;/title&gt;
&lt;/header&gt;
&lt;nav class="page-nav"&gt;Return to &lt;a href="../index.html"&gt;home&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;div class="main-bar"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Explaining git to the layperson&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;!-- 
    &lt;h2&gt;Readings&lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Articles that've stood out to me, or that I'd like to revisit:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://benn.substack.com/p/the-rise-of-the-analytics-pretendgineer"&gt;The rise of the analytics pretengineer&lt;/a&gt;, by benn.substack&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Useful concepts:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.macrometa.com/articles/what-is-the-difference-between-operational-data-and-transactional-data"&gt;Transactional vs operational data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Books I'm reading, in varying degrees of completion:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Fundamentals of Data Engineering, by Joe Reis and Matt Housley&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;The Data Warehouse Toolkit, 3rd Edition, by Ralph Kimball &amp; Margy Ross&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt; 
--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2024, I've had to explain how git works to a couple of people who don't know what it is, and this explanation seems to have worked:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Grasping versioning and collaboration using the GDrive analogy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know Google Drive? A git repository is like a Google Drive folder:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can create and store google docs, google sheets, and subfolders in it, as well as zipped files, text files, csv files, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can see the past versions of the documents and folders. In the version history, you can see what's been added or removed, as well as revert back to previous versions if you don't like the new changes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can share them with people, collaborate with them within the Drive, and give different collaborators different levels of access, making it either private or public, and you can work within the folder in real time, with collaborators editing different parts of it simultaneously.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So a git repo's like a Google Drive, but for code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, I ask them if they get the analogy and if they have questions. Once we clarify the latter, I guide them through setting up their IDE and cloning a repository (if there's an existing one they can work on) or creating a new git repository for a project. The idea's to ensure they have the tools to practice while they learn. It's fine if they don't get the meaning of &lt;code&gt;git clone&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;git init&lt;/code&gt; or the exact process behind these commands yet, but it's important they know they can return to that later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it's an existing repository, I walk them through its file structure in their IDE. If we're using GitHub, I walk them through the same thing there. If there's a particular file I want them to work on after this, I explain what it does and what's missing from it. Ideally it's a simple improvement that needs to be made, e.g. editing a couple of lines of code. Here, I want them to see the similarities between the files they have in their local computer and the files in GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Grasping branches using the tree analogy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I have the option to talk about branches. If the repository they're working on already uses branching and collaborators need to make pull requests, then I find this a good time to bring up the concept, lest it gets confusing later on. If it's their new personal repository where there's little likelihood of conflict should they pull from and push to main, then I could save the topic of branches and pull requests for later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To introduce branches and PRs, I pull out a diagram (adapted from &lt;a href="https://www.nobledesktop.com/learn/git/git-branches"&gt;noble desktop&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="A diagram of a git master branch with two child branches extending from it and merging back into it at different points in time" src="../images/git-branches-merge.png"/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine a tree. It has a trunk, out of which grow branches. That trunk, the main branch, is what you're seeing here: it contains code and files that produce the website you're seeing now or that produce whatever the files are telling the computer to produce (kinda). If you're using Visual Studio Code as the IDE, you can tell what branch you're on by looking for the branch's name on the bottom left of the editor. You can also open your terminal and enter the command &lt;code&gt;git branch&lt;/code&gt;; the asterik next to the branch name is, well, where you're at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's say you want to add a new feature to the site, or submit a change to the main branch. Enter &lt;code&gt;git checkout -b yourbranch&lt;/code&gt; in the terminal, and see how the name of the branch changes in the IDE, and how the asterik appears next to your new branch when you enter &lt;code&gt;git branch&lt;/code&gt; again. You're now on a little branch coming out of the main trunk, and this little branch is called &lt;code&gt;yourbranch&lt;/code&gt;. With the new branch created, you can switch between &lt;code&gt;main&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;yourbranch&lt;/code&gt; by using &lt;code&gt;git checkout main&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;git checkout yourbranch&lt;/code&gt; respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's here that I introduce them to &lt;a href="https://git-scm.com/docs/git"&gt;git's documentation&lt;/a&gt; and tell them about the &lt;code&gt;-b&lt;/code&gt; flag they used earlier and why they didn't have to include it when switching between branches. I want them to get into the habit of referring to documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I explain: You can play around with this branch as much as you like, without worrying about doing something that'd cause the main branch to go wonky. You also don't have to worry about someone else also playing around with the same set of code and overwriting your own in the same playground (yet), because they can make a new branch of their own, too. Eventually, once you're done with your edits, you want to request your fellow collaborators to review your work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; We call this raising a pull request. The aim of it is to get your collaborators to check through your code, and if they're okay with it, they'll approve it. That's when you can merge &lt;code&gt;yourbranch&lt;/code&gt; into &lt;code&gt;main&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I stop here for a clarity check: do they have any questions?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Grasping the git workflow by making their first pull request&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enough of high-level explanations; it's time to make those edits. I watch them do it in &lt;code&gt;yourbranch&lt;/code&gt;, save it, and then I pull out a diagram (adapted from &lt;a href="https://www.freecodecamp.org/news/learn-the-basics-of-git-in-under-10-minutes-da548267cc91"&gt;freecodecamp&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="A black and white diagram of git commands like git add, commit, push, merge, fetch and pull, and how they work" src="../images/git-workflow-diagram.png"/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I point to the working directory. "Your changes are here now," I tell them, "and your aim is to get them ready for a pull request by your collaborators. So you'll need to get your changes to here instead," and I point to the remote repository (main). I open up GitHub and navigate to the repository. "Once you do that, you'll see your changes reflected here."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, it gets a bit messy, but I try to tie my explanations back to previous analogies, while introducing new commands:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure out where you are with &lt;code&gt;git status&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Enter &lt;code&gt;git status&lt;/code&gt; in the terminal and read to me what the output says. It should indicate we're on &lt;code&gt;yourbranch&lt;/code&gt; and that there are untracked files. "Use &lt;code&gt;git add&lt;/code&gt; to include in what will be committed," it writes, so try that command and enter &lt;code&gt;git status&lt;/code&gt; again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;git add&lt;/code&gt; to the staging area&lt;/strong&gt;: See those green lines? They're the files you just added, and you've added them to what we call the staging area. This is where I make reference to the diagram. Then, I tell them to make more changes to a file they just added, small ones, like changing a comment or a piece of copy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enter &lt;code&gt;git status&lt;/code&gt; again and note how the filename reappears in the outputted red text, under the section that writes, "Changes not staged for commit (use &lt;code&gt;git add&lt;/code&gt; or use &lt;code&gt;git restore&lt;/code&gt;)". You can &lt;code&gt;git add&lt;/code&gt; that file once again to the staging area, or maybe you don't like that new change, and you can enter &lt;code&gt;git restore&lt;/code&gt;. This staging area is your playground; you can add or remove things from it however you like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Check the version history with &lt;code&gt;git log&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Remember how a git repository is like a Google Drive folder? Just like how you can view the version history of your google doc, you can do the same with your files using &lt;code&gt;git log&lt;/code&gt;. There shouldn't be anything of note there yet, except for the output to tell you that &lt;code&gt;HEAD -&amp;gt; yourbranch, origin/main&lt;/code&gt;. Type &lt;code&gt;q&lt;/code&gt; in the terminal to stop printing out the logs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;git commit&lt;/code&gt; to the local repository&lt;/strong&gt;: Once you've amended a bunch of files and you're ready to commit to your changes, enter &lt;code&gt;git commit -m "a message about your changes"&lt;/code&gt; in the terminal. Now you can type &lt;code&gt;git log&lt;/code&gt; again and read the different output. You can continue making a bunch of edits, and you can add all the edits related to some same task (e.g. remove comments from all files) to the staging area, upon which you can commit them to your local repository using &lt;code&gt;git commit&lt;/code&gt; and a useful message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Publish &lt;code&gt;yourbranch&lt;/code&gt; as a remote repository and &lt;code&gt;git push&lt;/code&gt; to it&lt;/strong&gt;: Once you've gathered all your edits around some central theme (e.g. build a new feature on a website) and tested it, and you're ready to get it reviewed by your collaborators, enter &lt;code&gt;git push&lt;/code&gt; in your terminal. The first time you do this, it's not going to work, and here I tell them to not freak out at it not working, and instead, read the terminal's output. Run the command as it says to publish the branch, and it's going to net you a link to a pull request that you can open.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open a pull request&lt;/strong&gt;: The main things I explain here, after following the link, are the request review button and the fact that you can tag collaborators in your comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Approved? Merge it to the main remote repository&lt;/strong&gt;: Get them to press merge to main. They'll see their changes show up in the remote repository, and it's here that it's quite nice to watch them go, "Oh!" when they see that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;git checkout&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;main&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;git pull&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: To close the loop, have them return to their &lt;code&gt;main&lt;/code&gt; branch in their terminal, and merge/pull the changes they just made in &lt;code&gt;yourbranch&lt;/code&gt; from either the local repository (assuming it's up to date and no other collaborator has pushed and merge changes of their own to &lt;code&gt;main&lt;/code&gt;) or the remote repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's still a lot to take in, but the main points that helped me explain these concepts live and that I want to stress are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emphasising they should reference documentation and online guides when they're stuck&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Getting them to practise relaxing and reading the terminal's output; don't panic at the sight of errors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw simple diagrams and reference them often when you're talking or when they're asking questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get them to explain the concept you're teaching them back to you, even if they say they get it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask them to work on another round of edits, but to open a PR of their own this time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before and after the session, I point them to a couple of readings:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.github.com/en/pull-requests/collaborating-with-pull-requests/proposing-changes-to-your-work-with-pull-requests"&gt;GitHub Docs' Collaborate with pull requests&lt;/a&gt;: Specifically the sections on about branches, creating/deleting branches and creating a pull request&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://missing.csail.mit.edu/2020/version-control/"&gt;Version Control (git)&lt;/a&gt;, by missing semester of your CS education&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;]]&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate></item><item><title>How to press flowers</title><link>https://commonplace-journal.pages.dev/pages/how-to-press-flowers.html</link><guid>46a414ba340263a111fa2c19d591131c</guid><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;body data-tags="art"&gt;
&lt;header&gt;
&lt;title&gt;How to press flowers&lt;/title&gt;
&lt;/header&gt;
&lt;nav class="page-nav"&gt;Return to &lt;a href="../index.html"&gt;home&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;div class="main-bar"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;How to press flowers&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Materials used&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I watched a couple of YouTube tutorials to see what I needed, and it took 1-2 batches of pressed flowers (that came out in varying quality) before I settled on a routine. I didn't need fancy tools, like presses made of wood and cardboard and weights as heavy as bricks. I made use of what I had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Paper material&lt;/b&gt;: the more absorbent the better, but photocopy paper works alright. I keep a stack of mail I don't need and reuse them as flower pressing paper.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Weight&lt;/b&gt;: books, ceramic plates, computers, etc. as long as the bottom's flat and weight's distributed evenly across it. Depending on the pressing method, I use either books or plates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;A source of plants&lt;/b&gt;: I'll expand on this in one of the below sections, especially on the ethics of it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nice to have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Microwave&lt;/b&gt;: only if you're using the microwave method, though I use it most of the time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Tweezers&lt;/b&gt;: helpful for moving small and delicate plant material around, especially when they're the sort to be stuck limply to paper prior to drying.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Containers / binders&lt;/b&gt; as storage space for pressed flowers: I use plastic containers that local hawker centres give out to store sauces when I get takeaway; they're great for small flowers. For bigger flowers, I slide them in between the plain pages of a cheap sketchbook, though I've seen others slide them between papers and store those papers in a plastic folder, or keep them between pages of old, bound tutorial notes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Starting out&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had no idea what worked and didn't work. Lots of online tutorials said the traditional method of using a book press, i.e. leaving a flower in between the pages of a thick book, stacking more heavy books on top of it, and forgetting about it for four weeks, works wonders for them. The flower and leaves turn out great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was not the case for mine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd picked up a couple of flowers from the sidewalk while wandering in my neighborhood. I figured if book-presses worked for centuries, it can't hurt to try it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I left my flowers in between copy paper of mail and put them between old books. I checked them after a day, then after two days, and wow: a couple of flowers maintained their color's vibrancy, but most, disappointingly, browned or blackened. They didn't rot and fall apart; they &lt;i&gt;dried&lt;/i&gt;, but they didn't look too hot. Instead of being excited about what I'd do with the dried flowers, I betted which ones would make it and which would not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also didn't know when the flowers were considered done. At the one-week mark, I thought they were dry. Then at the two-week mark, I thought, "Surely they have to be ready." At the three-week mark, I thought the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, though, I know what dry flowers look - and feel - like. I also know which flower species press well, and which didn't. I know when to use book-presses and when to use other methods, like a microwave. People online recommend ways such as pressing them with an iron without water, or buying a professional flower press, but I figured it'd be fine to leave those alone; I'd found what worked for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The science behind how flowers get pressed and preserved&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter what method's used, the aim of flower pressing is to dry and flatten them. That's how they're able to last for decades: by geeting water content out of their petals, stems or leaves, they're less likely to rot, even if they turn brown or fade in color.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, if you stick your flowers/leaves in between books and leave them alone, the aim &lt;i&gt;isn't&lt;/i&gt; to squish them till they're as flat as possible. You might just end up with a squished, wet and rotting plant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you flatten your plant between paper material and put it in a microwave or under an iron, the aim's &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; to burn or squeeze it flat; the aim's to evaporate the water content with just enough heat, while the paper material absorbs the plant's moisture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Factors affecting the effectiveness of flower pressing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the effectiveness of flower pressing depends on a few factors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your climate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plant species&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Colour of flower&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plant's stage of life&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Absorbency of the paper used and the air circulation your plants get during pressing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Temperature and duration of heat in a microwave&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How you store them after pressing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Your climate&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;The more humid and warmer where you are, the longer it'll take for your plant material to dry out in the open. I've seen brown, fallen leaves perfectly dried and preserved in the dead of winter of a semi-arid / arid location, while flowers remain damp even after weeks of being book-pressed in Singapore.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Plant species&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;I've heard from online sources that tropical flowers don't press well, but being in the tropics, tropical flowers is what I can find. There aren't as many resources out there for pressing tropical flowers, so finding this out took trial and error. Ixoras do great in book-presses and microwaves alike. Frangipanis, crossandras and yellow bells maintain their colours' vibrancy for months after I microwave them a little, and are also alright if I leave them in between papers afterwards. Petunias do okay in microwaves but terribly in book-presses. The sole orchid (a vanda miss joaquim / papilionanthe miss joaqium) I picked up from the ground did not press well at &lt;i&gt;all&lt;/i&gt;; it stuck wetly to the paper in the microwave. So it depends on the amount of water content their petals hold, and whether they have thick stems or receptacles that you might want to cut away or cut in half so they dry more quickly.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Colour of flower&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;I've given up trying to pick up and press white flowers; they turn yellow by the time I get them into the press or after I dry them. Colours that have done well seem to be red/orange/yellow, as well as purple/blue. I've noticed pink flowers tend to become brown really quickly; my pink petunias all turn brownish after drying, while the dark purple ones retain its hue, though at times unevenly.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Plant's stage of life&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;I've read online that the fresher the flower, the better able it's able to retain its original colour. I don't pluck flowers from public gardens as I don't think it's right, but it does mean I don't know much about comparing the pressing quality of a newly bloomed flower snipped from the stem, versus a flower that's recently fallen off. But I did notice that the more wilted the flower's become, the more yellow and limp it'll be. Brown spots become darker and more pronounced after drying, and if you're using the book-press in a warm / not well-circulated area, the brown spots spread.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Absorbency of the paper used and the air circulation your plants get during pressing&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;I researched why my original book-press didn't work. Turns out, the important thing to do in a book-press and professional flower press is to set the plant between layers of different absorbent materials. Recommended materials include: newspapers, flat corrugated cardboard and blotting papers. The corrugated cardboard, especially, contains air holes that allow air to circulate through the layers, which allows the moisture to evaporate out from them rather than stay trapped in the paper, causing the plant to rot anyway. This plus the tropical humidity of my first book-press attempt turned my plants into dark yellows and browns. While I don't care much for air circulation in a microwave, for thick or damp flowers, I might add more layers of paper around the plant, so the water has a place to escape to, from the petals.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Temperature and duration of heat in a microwave&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;I didn't want to burn / fry my flowers into crisps by leaving them in the microwave for too long. I normally press the plant between photocopy paper, set a plate on top of it, and heat the plant in 15 - 30 second intervals, usually to a maximum of 2 minutes. After every interval, I take out the plant and let the heat dissisipate till it's at room temperature. Depending on your microwave's settings and power, the interval duration could differ. There's no rule to this; I just gave a few options a shot.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;How you store them after pressing&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;I keep the pressed flowers out of sunlight / artificial light, as their colours are known to fade in the light. For big flowers and leaves, I keep them between paper, which keeps them dry; they'll still rot if they collect moisture from the air. For small flowers, putting them in plastic containers, then storing those containers in dry drawers, works for me.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How to know when a pressed flower's ready&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I run my finger across the petal or leaf. Does it feel like paper? If yes, it's dry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A redditor on &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/PressedFlowers/"&gt;r/PressedFlowers&lt;/a&gt; gave this response to someone else asking this question. Back then, I didn't understand what they meant. I'd run my finger along the petal as instructed and went, "Does this feel like paper?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I didn't realise is that if I had to ask myself that question, it meant the plant wasn't dry. The flowers had been in my first book-press and it'd been week two out of four. It hadn't yet dried, but it'd felt limp and fragile and stuck a little to my fingerpad when I pressed on it and lifted it up. If the petals do that, or if they wrinkle, sticking slightly to the paper, at your touch, it's still a tad damp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It feels unmistakably like paper once it dries, but it's something you'll have to wait and experience personally to understand the feeling, if you're a first-time flower presser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Finding plants for pressing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Where and when to collect plants&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use the flowers that have fallen to the ground in my neighbourhood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best time to find those are after it rains. The flowers and leaves are freshly hydrated with a vibrant sheen, and the force of the rain causes a whole lot of them to detach and drop. The only additional thing I'd do after collecting them is to let them dry a little, out in the open, on my desk or kitchen counter, so there's less water to evaporate in the microwave or absorb in the book-press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've picked up flowers that've been out in the afternoon sun before, and they often look limp with spots of yellow-brown. They're more than alright to press; they'll just look more faded from the harsh light and heat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The ethics of collecting plants from public spaces&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, I had no issue picking up a fallen flower from the side of the road. I still don't feel &lt;i&gt;bad&lt;/i&gt;, but I began to remember the signboards in national parks of American and European countries requesting that visitors leave no trace of themselves behind, as well as take nothing with them but themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do the same guidelines apply for wildflowers and wilting flowers on the pavement?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've never paid much attention to flowers, much less plants, grown in my country. Since picking up this hobby, though, I've never paid so much attention to the different species here and the characteristics they have. These days, I stop and watch the flowers, even if I don't pick them up from the ground. Interacting and spending time with them made me observe them; before, I was a passerby in the city I live in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't think it's right to grab them fresh from their stalks. I suppose you could do the latter if you get government authorisation, but from my past experiences, I've found that those granted with a licence to collect - and kill - live flora and fauna for educational or research purposes tend to treat the wildlife like they own them. You've been granted permission for a limited amount of time to trap those bugs and snip those plants, so you do it. So what if you trample on some undergrowth? You're empowered by those up-top, from those with power larger than that of the individual. Not arguing that researchers and students should stop collecting species for study, but such a relationship between the researcher and the wildlife feels... scary. Exploitative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, if I want to monetize this in the future, I don't think it'll be right to grab the fallen plants from public areas either. I'll need to source them from proper vendors, collection flowers discarded during events or grow them myself. But as a hobby? I've never been more motivated to walk in gardens recently, or never have I felt more like an actual resident of my neighbourhood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;]]&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate></item><item><title>SQL query optimization</title><link>https://commonplace-journal.pages.dev/pages/sql-query-optimization.html</link><guid>3db719078f264e2c9c22e00a506a42ec</guid><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;body data-tags="tech and data"&gt;
&lt;header&gt;
&lt;title&gt;SQL query optimization&lt;/title&gt;
&lt;/header&gt;
&lt;nav class="page-nav"&gt;Return to &lt;a href="../index.html"&gt;home&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;div class="main-bar"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;SQL query optimization&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the annoying problems I've been facing at work is making my SQL queries in Snowflake run more quickly. It didn't use to be a problem I thought about, because the previous pressing issue had been to make a dataset available in the first place, to get a set of dashboards up and running in the first place, speed and performance be damned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that those &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; up and running, having slow queries and slower dashboards are a pain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But to make any speed improvement, I must first understand query profiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transactional table vs operational table&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;]]&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><lastBuildDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate></item><item><title>Attending the Climate Change AI Summer School 2024</title><link>https://commonplace-journal.pages.dev/pages/attending-the-climate-change-ai-summer-school-2024.html</link><guid>9d87351266209c73dd47a54b9acf54ae</guid><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;body data-tags="climate change; tech and data; courses"&gt;
&lt;header&gt;&lt;title&gt;Attending the Climate Change AI Summer School 2024&lt;/title&gt;&lt;/header&gt;
&lt;nav class="page-nav"&gt;Return to &lt;a href="../index.html"&gt;home&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;div class="main-bar"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Attending the Climate Change AI Summer School 2024&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;About CCAI&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Climate Change AI (CCAI) is a non-profit I've followed for a while (they have a newsletter). This year was the first time I signed up for their &lt;a href="https://www.climatechange.ai/events/summer_school2024"&gt;annual summer school&lt;/a&gt;, where they get professors and industry speakers to give introductory lectures about the use of AI/ML techniques in different domains of climate change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I paid 30 SGD for access to a series of virtual lectures and tutorials, most of which were honestly pretty solid! You don't have to complete everything, and access is indefinite after payment, though you do get a certificate if you submit at least eight assessments/feedback forms before the summer ends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Lectures and thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the lectures I watched. I've starred the ones I thought stood out in terms of the comprehensiveness of content, the quality of delivery, and where I felt I learned a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/99U0ePt9DzY"&gt;Introduction to AI for Agriculture&lt;/a&gt; (Prof Hannah Kerner, NASA Harvest &amp;amp; ASU Center for Global Discovery and Conservation Science @ Arizona State University) ★&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;A crash course on the relationship between agriculture and climate change. Opportunities for AI/ML lie in the intersections between remote sensing, agriculture/food security and in-situ sensing. Prof Kerner covered a lot of ground about what stakeholders want and the common types of datasets used too.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/99U0ePt9DzY?feature=shared&amp;amp;t=3788"&gt;Forests &amp;amp; Land Systems&lt;/a&gt; (Dr David Dao, Gainforest.Earth &amp;amp; ETH BiodivX)&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;My key takeaways from this lecture: 1) ML processes high volumes of public remote imagery efficiently, 2) ML turns manual reporting of situations on the ground into machine-assisted reporting. Dr Dao interspersed it with forest soundscapes and personal photographs from his work at Gainforest.Earth, a non-profit he cofounded. This was the first time I learned that applying AI/ML on bioacoustics was an active field of study.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=I9TIRncO9HE&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be"&gt;Machine learning for animal conservation: from sensors to knowledge&lt;/a&gt; (Davis Tuia, ECEO Laboratory, EPFL) ★&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Prof Tuia structured this presentation super well, keeping the overview concise. He spent juicy amounts of time covering how sensors collect biodiversity data and four different ML approaches for conservation (detection and localisation of animals, individual identification, posture estimation and environmental reconstruction).&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/I9TIRncO9HE?feature=shared&amp;amp;t=3830"&gt;AI for Conservation Decisions&lt;/a&gt; (Lily Xu, University of Oxford &amp;amp; Columbia University)&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;AI/ML opportunities in conservation efforts were pretty theoretical in this presentation. Prof Xu focused on drawing parallels between classical ML applications with how they are currently used -- but mostly how they can be potentially used -- in conservation (e.g. predicting where poachers place animal traps to optimise rangers' patrol paths, given constraints such as rangers' limited number of hours).&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=q-rbAyZuZjo"&gt;Climate Innovation Policy&lt;/a&gt; (Alice Lépissier, Green Finance AI) ★&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Dr Lépissier's presentation blew me away. The segment on AI/ML opportunities in climate innovation policymaking was brief. But she made me understand, finally, how the state's financial engineering efforts derisk and foster the private sector's innovation in climate tech, because technological innovation can't exist in a vacuum. E.g. EV cars in California would not have taken off as much as it did without state-offered incentives to encourage its adoption. Reducing emissions is important, but progress will not sustain unless we replace the current economy with a low-carbon one, and it's financial incentives/carrots (e.g. subsidies, and not just disincentives/sticks like carbon taxes) that'll get us there. Like, wow? Suddenly the buzzwords clicked together; green finance used to be a black box to me.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=P5_R_5kJDas"&gt;AI for Climate Science&lt;/a&gt; (Kai Jeggle, ETH Zürich &amp;amp; CCAI)&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Introduced basic atmospheric science theory and how climate data's characteristics (e.g. non-linear relationships between variables, high volume) make it suitable for ML research. AI models are also cheaper to run than traditional climate models. Raised two examples of ML applications and the main challenges this field faces.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/P5_R_5kJDas?feature=shared&amp;amp;t=3788"&gt;An introduction to AI for weather forecasting&lt;/a&gt; (Peetak Mitra, Excarta)&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;A highly technical lecture on short/medium-term weather forecast models used in the industry, especially vision and SWIN transformers. Not all terms are defined, so will need to do some independent research!&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=j3_jE0ZqsMM"&gt;Machine learning for emissions accounting and monitoring&lt;/a&gt; (Kasia Tokarska de los Santos, CarbonPool)&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Taught GHG Protocol's definitions of Scope 1-3. High-level presentation of ML techniques reported by papers and organisations in emissions accounting (e.g. predicting missing corporate emissions from voluntarily reported ESG metrics) and monitoring (e.g. estimating regional emissions through remote sensing of biomass).&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jJsRRDy3WHQ"&gt;Empirical quantification of how the climate impacts socio-economic outcomes&lt;/a&gt; (Jonathan Proctor, University of British Columbia) ★&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;This was an amazing lecture. It's not exactly &lt;em&gt;AI&lt;/em&gt;, but I began to understand how climate scientists isolate and quantify relationships between climate variables (e.g. temperature, soil moisture) and some outcome (e.g. human mortality, crop yield), while accounting for variations across time and space, as well as datasets with varying granularities.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RJ__2-qViCM"&gt;Role of data and AI for climate change mitigation and adaptation in cities&lt;/a&gt; (Angel Hsu, Data-Driven EnviroLab, University of North Carolina-Chapel Hill)&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;A high-level overview of how applying NLP techniques and generative AI on policy papers is key to understanding how cities mitigate climate change effects, as well as how geospatial analytics enable cities to adapt to climate change.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/RJ__2-qViCM?feature=shared&amp;amp;t=3720"&gt;(Geo)AI for Buildings and Cities&lt;/a&gt; (Filip Biljecki, Urban Analytics Lab @ National University of Singapore)&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Finding high volumes of quality data about buildings is a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; challenge. Prof Biljecki spent significant time covering emerging datasets and how they're mined/generated: street view imagery, user-generated geographic information (e.g. OpenStreetMap, real estate ads), AI models that generate building data, programmes to collect occupant information from wearables. Covered a bit about developing metrics to characterise buildings, as well as data quality and model accuracy.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G5VuaWaYsLU"&gt;GHG Impact Assessment of AI&lt;/a&gt; (Lynn Kaack, Hertie School &amp;amp; CCAI and George Kamiya, led IEA's analysis on energy/climate impact of digitalisation)&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Kamiya led the lecture on  AI/ML's compute-related impacts, while Prof Kaack led the one on system-level impacts. The main takeaways were 1) we lack data to understand how ML uses energy, and 2) governmental organisations are developing regulation, monitoring programmes and research initiatives to understand ML's societal impacts. The value here lies in their references to other studies, programmes and publications.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/G5VuaWaYsLU?feature=shared&amp;amp;t=3735"&gt;Responsible AI and Sustainability&lt;/a&gt; (Dr Sasha Luccioni, Hugging Face, Women in Machine Learning &amp;amp; CCAI) ★&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Insightful presentation about the theory vs practice of implementing ethical, sustainable AI. She also introduced recurring themes in this topic's research: representativeness of AI models, their transparency, equity, and how they're evaluated for metrics beyond accuracy, such as models' fairness, data quality, robustness and efficiency.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=L8CYBqgAPAc&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be"&gt;ML for Power &amp;amp; Energy Systems&lt;/a&gt; (Prof Priya L Donti, EECS &amp;amp; LIDS and Dr Nsutezo Simone Fobi, Microsoft AI for Good Research Lab) ★&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Solid overview of how ML's applied in the operations, planning, innovation and data management of power systems, and how it can improved our understanding of the energy market. Introduces the domain of electric grids, too, and emphasises the importance of being practical with the ML used.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i23jr7pkjsM&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be"&gt;AI for Transportation&lt;/a&gt; (Nikola Milojevic-Dupont @ MCC Berlin &amp;amp; Felix Wagner @ Technical University Berlin)&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Speakers broke the lecture into two sections: covering an overview of the transport sector and its emissions, followed by specific examples of how AI/ML's used in it. The interactive exercises, e.g. developing metrics and gathering datasets on demand trip forecasting, seemed especially useful in getting the audience to think.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3mtbFx_8VVc"&gt;Artificial Intelligence for Planetary Health: Challenges, Opportunities, and Human Choice&lt;/a&gt; (Prof Sara Khalid, Planetary Health Informatics Lab &amp;amp; Centre for Statistics in Medicine @ University of Oxford)&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Brief overview of planetary health analytics, including the applications (e.g. early warning systems for flood, heat, disease outbreaks, etc.), how datasets from patients and about the climate can be geographically linked for analysis, and challenges faced in this field (e.g. biased data).&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;]]&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 07 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate></item></channel></rss>